Since 2003, a special type of scam targeting the elderly
Od roku 2003 w Japonii króluje biorące na cel osoby starsze
called the money transfer scam has proliferated in Japan.
oszustwo zwane „przekrętem na przelew”.
Financial damages increased every year, reaching 56.5 billion yen in 2014.
Straty finansowe rosną z roku na rok. W 2014 r. wynosiły 56,5 miliarda jenów.
Now, in 2019, scammers have changed their techniques,
W 2019 roku oszuści zmienili metody,
and the damage continues.
w dalszym ciągu okradając obywateli.
Careful!
Uwaga!
Get him in!
Do środka z nim!
Shut your mouth!
Stul dziób!
Let go of me!
Puszczaj!
I'm the manager!
Jestem kierownikiem!
Shit!
O cholera!
-Get out! -Come on!
- Wyłaź! - Idziemy!
Move!
Ruchy!
Hurry up!
Szybciej!
Stop struggling!
Nie szarp się!
Sit down!
Siadaj!
Good morning!
Dzieńdoberek!
EPISODE 5
ODCINEK 5
Thanks for making it out here, Mr. Manager.
Dzięki za wizytę, kierowniku.
What are you trying to achieve by doing this?
Co chcesz przez to osiągnąć?
You wanna rat me out to Kanbe?
Chcesz na mnie donieść?
Why don't you at least hear me out?
Może mnie choć wysłuchasz?
If you do, you might just have a change of heart.
Może zmienisz zdanie.
Hear you out? About what?
Co niby chcesz mi powiedzieć?
I'm going to rob you!
Okradniemy was!
Well, to be precise, we're going after Kanbe.
Kanbego, ściślej mówiąc.
He's opened up nine stores now, right?
Ma już dziewięć oddziałów.
If we do this right, the payoff will be unbelievable.
Jeśli to się uda, zarobimy fortunę.
I want information!
Potrzebuję informacji!
-Information? -About Kanbe's movements.
- Jakich? - O planach Kanbego.
I haven't been able to find any of his weaknesses yet.
Nie znam jego słabości.
Of course, you'd get a cut as well.
Tobie też coś skapnie.
How about ten percent?
Co powiesz na dziesięć procent?
It's a good deal, right?
Może być?
Give me a high five!
Piąteczka!
It hurts!
Boli!
Come on now.
Daj spokój.
You know, this is your little punk friend's fault.
To wina twojego durnego kumpla.
I'm sorry, but...
Przykro mi, ale...
you've left me without a choice!
nie pozostawiasz mi wyboru!
-Go ahead and do it. -What?
- Śmiało. - Co?
You're going to fail. Mark my words.
Przegrasz. Zapamiętaj moje słowa.
-You little... -How dare you!
- Ty gnoju... - Jak śmiesz!
Wait, wait, wait!
Czekajcie!
You've piqued my interest.
To ciekawe.
What exactly do you mean by that?
Co masz na myśli?
Isn't it obvious?
Czy to nie oczywiste?
You and Kanbe-san aren't even in the same universe.
Ty i pan Kanbe to dwa różne światy.
You don't stand a chance.
Nie masz szans.
What a disappointment.
Rozczarowałeś mnie.
I thought you'd say something a little more clever.
Spodziewałem się czegoś mądrzejszego.
Here.
Proszę.
Okay, okay.
No dobrze.
It hurts!
To boli!
Of course it hurts, you idiot!
Ma boleć, durniu!
If I'm not careful, you could die!
Jak nie będę uważał, to zdechniesz.
I'm going to barbecue you!
Usmażę cię!
Hey, hey, hey, hey, until you agree to help,
Jeśli mi nie pomożesz,
I'm going to roast every last piece of your body to the bone.
upiekę cię na wolnym ogniu, kawałek po kawałeczku.
So? Will you do it? Will you help me steal from Kanbe?
To jak? Pomożesz mi go okraść?
All right then. Well, tell me when you change your mind.
Jak chcesz. Daj znać, gdy zmienisz zdanie.
Here we go!
Jedziemy!
-Stop! -Good evening.
- Dość! - Dobry wieczór.
Is this the Yamada residence?
Mieszka tu pan Yamada?
No! Can't you see that for yourself?
Nie! Nie widać?
It's not?
Co?
I must have gotten it wrong.
Musiałem pomylić adres.
Sorry about that.
Przepraszam.
-Who the hell was that? -He walked off.
- Kto to był? - Poszedł sobie.
Hey, don't just stand there like an idiot.
Nie stój jak baran.
What if he tells someone?
A jak komuś powie?
-Go follow him! -Yes, sir!
- Za nim! - Tak jest!
Excuse me, is this the Yamada residence?
Przepraszam, mieszka tu pan Yamada?
Hey! Hurry up and stop him!
Szybko, łapać go!
-Yamada-san? -He's bothering the neighbors.
- Pan Yamada? - Zaczepia sąsiadów.
Is this the Yamada residence?
Mieszka tu pan Yamada?
Who is that? A friend of yours?
To jakiś twój koleś?
-Whatever. Make him sit down on the chair. -Is there a Yamada here?
- Nieważne. Posadź go. - Jest pan Yamada?
-What are you doing? -Excuse me?
- Co ty robisz? - Proszę?
Are you high or something?
Naćpany jesteś?
Whatever. So? What you gonna do?
Nieważne. Co mi zrobisz?
Stop it!
Przestańcie!
Hey! Don't do that!
Nie rób tego!
I'm sorry! I said I'm sorry!
Przepraszam!
Please! Save me!
Błagam, oszczędź mnie!
What the hell is going on? Carlos, go check it out.
Co tam się dzieje? Sprawdź to, Carlos.
What? Me?
Co? Ja?
Yes, you!
Tak, ty!
I'm Yamada. That's Makoto.
Jestem Yamada, a to jest Makoto.
-I'm Carlos. -So, it's you, then!
- Carlos. - Czyli ty!
I said go check it out!
Ruchy!
Hey, who did you call here?
Kogo tu sprowadziłeś?
-I don't know him. -Liar!
- Nie znam go. - Łżesz!
Help me!
Pomocy!
I'm going to kill you!
Zabiję cię!
So, you are Yamada-san?
Ty jesteś Yamada?
Yes, I'm Yamada!
Tak, to ja!
Makoto, help me!
Makoto, pomóż mi!
I'll apologize to Kanbe, I swear! Mako--
Przeproszę Kanbego, przysięgam!
-Makoto! -I'll be leaving, then.
- Makoto! - Na mnie już czas.
Makoto! Makoto! Hey!
Makoto!
Hey! Say thank you to Seimiya.
Podziękuj Seimiyi.
He saw you getting kidnapped and called me right away.
Widział, że cię porwano, i mnie poinformował.
It's a good thing he remembered the license plate number.
Dobrze, że zapamiętał rejestrację.
We know the plate numbers and addresses of everyone who works for us.
Znamy numery i adresy wszystkich pracowników.
That's why I was able to send help so quickly.
Dlatego odsiecz przybyła tak szybko.
Who is that person?
Kto to był?
Onuma.
Onuma.
Onuma?
Onuma?
He's a jack-of-all-trades of sorts.
Specjalista w wielu dziedzinach.
You probably won't be seeing him again, so forget about it.
I tak już go pewnie nie spotkasz.
What happened to Yamada-san?
Co się stało z Yamadą?
Yamada...
Yamada...
I wish I could meet with him and express my gratitude one more time.
Chciałbym jeszcze raz go spotkać i móc mu podziękować.
After all, he's the one who introduced you to this job.
W końcu to on cię nam przedstawił.
I'm in his debt.
Jestem jego dłużnikiem.
-Kusano. -Yes?
- Kusano. - Tak?
You've passed the point of no return.
Teraz nie ma już odwrotu.
You have to put your life on the line for this job.
Za tę pracę musisz być gotów oddać życie.
You can't go back to your normal life, now. So...
Do swojego życia już nie wrócisz.
now you need to do whatever it takes to make money.
Teraz zrobisz wszystko, by zarobić szmal.
Mom?
Mama?
Hey.
Cześć.
You're alive?
Ty żyjesz?
I'm sorry for what I did.
Przepraszam za wszystko.
I'm apologizing, so can you call Kanbe off?
Przepraszam. Odwołasz Kanbego?
You know I can't do that.
Wiesz, że nie mogę.
There's no going back.
Nie ma już odwrotu.
To what?
Od czego?
-There's no going back. -What?
- Nie ma już odwrotu. - Co?
-There's no-- -Please stop!
- Nie ma... - Przestań!
There's no going back for you now.
Dla ciebie nie ma już odwrotu!
You can't go back! You can't go back!
Już nie zawrócisz!
-Stop! -You...
- Przestań! - Dla ciebie...
can't go back.
nie ma już odwrotu.
Starting today, we're changing things.
Czas na zmiany.
We've hit seven targets this week
W tym tygodniu oskubaliśmy siedem celów,
and made 36 million yen.
zarabiając 36 milionów.
Our hit rate is through the roof, thanks to the new register,
Dzięki nowemu rejestrowi mamy świetne wyniki,
but at this rate, we'll use it up in no time.
ale w tym tempie zaraz go wykorzystamy.
It'll be difficult to reach our quota of 120 million.
Ciężko będzie dobić do 120 milionów.
That's true. We only have 400 targets left.
Fakt, zostało 400 osób.
That's why we're changing things. Gouriki.
Dlatego czas na zmiany. Gouriki.
Put aside the new contacts and go for the seven targets we've already hit.
Zostaw nowe cele i dzwoń do dotychczasowych.
Use the rager act to bleed them dry.
Zagraj wściekłego i wyczyść im konta.
Fine, but if I push it too hard, they'll go to the police.
Jeśli przesadzę, pójdą na policję.
If that happens, tell them that even if you're arrested,
Powiedz, że jeśli cię aresztują,
your friends will go after them.
dopadną ich twoi kumple.
Even if it's a bluff, as long as we scare them, we win.
To ściema, ale jeśli się wystraszą, dobra nasza.
We have to get them to pay as much as they can.
Musimy wycisnąć, ile się da.
-Got it. -Seimiya.
- Jasne. - Seimiya.
Do you know the dead person scam?
Znasz przekręt na trupa?
I've heard of it.
Słyszałem.
You tell targets that their deceased relative borrowed money, right?
Mówisz celom, że ich bliski zmarły miał długi.
Right. This register has the name, death date and professions
W rejestrze mamy nazwiska, daty zgonu i zawody
of the targets' recently deceased husbands and wives.
zmarłych małżonków celów.
This information will definitely help.
Te informacje nam pomogą.
Take Kurusu and Mori and modify the scripts from the illegitimate child
Weź Kurutsu i Moriego. Zmieńcie scenariusz nieślubnego dziecka
and embezzlement bluffs to make it work.
i defraudacji, żeby coś z tego złożyć.
Got it.
Jasne.
Hey...
Czekajcie...
This register shows how much money some of the targets are keeping at home.
Z rejestru wiemy, ile forsy trzymają w domu.
Maybe we could lure them out of the house
Możemy ich wywabić
and go in and filch the place as soon as they leave.
i wyczyścić im chałupy.
"Filch"?
„Wyczyścić”?
It means rob.
Obrabować.
Don't be an idiot.
Nie bądź głupi.
Why? It'll be quick.
No co? Chwila strachu.
Our job is to scam people.
My robimy przekręty.
-If we start robbing people, that's-- -A crime.
- Włamania to... - Przestępstwo.
Scamming is also a crime.
Tak jak oszustwa.
-It's a business. -Let's put that aside for now.
- To biznes. - Mniejsza o semantykę.
Actually, I know a few people who could help us out.
Znam parę osób, które mogą nam pomóc.
If we give them a cut, they'll do it.
Wystarczy im odpalić działkę.
-Absolutely not. -Why not? It's a good idea.
- Nie ma mowy. - To dobry pomysł.
I don't need ideas like that.
Nie chcę takich pomysłów.
We won't be using any means outside of scamming.
Pozostaniemy przy przekrętach.
Start with what I just told you.
Zacznijcie od tego, co mówiłem.
-Let's do it. -Okay.
- Do dzieła. - Jasne.
Fine.
Niech będzie.
Himeka?
Himeka?
-What's wrong? -Misaki...
- Co się stało? - Misaki...
I was told not to say anything, but...
Miałam nic nie mówić, ale...
-Takezo-san... -What?
- Panie Takezo... - Tak?
How did it get like this in a week?
Taki bałagan w tydzień?
I told you, I've got back pain!
Mówiłem, że bolą mnie plecy!
What if I hurt my back trying to stand up?
A jak coś sobie zrobię, wstając?
Would you take responsibility if that happened?
Odpowie pani za to?
But...
Ale...
You're just an employee,
Zatrudniam panią,
so stop telling me what to do! I'm paying for this!
więc proszę mi nie rozkazywać! Płacę za to!
Now clean all of this up. Come on!
A teraz proszę to posprzątać. Ruchy!
Not again...
Znowu to samo.
I'm sorry. I did it again.
Przepraszam, znów to samo.
Now that I'm older, I lose my temper so easily.
Na starość często wybucham.
I'm sorry, Kusano-san. I'm sorry!
Przepraszam panią.
Don't worry. It's okay.
Nie szkodzi.
You don't have to clean anymore,
Nie musi pani sprzątać.
so come here and sit with me for a bit.
Proszę ze mną posiedzieć.
I'll just clean this up real quick.
Szybko to ogarnę.
Let's watch some TV! Look, I have some snacks.
Pooglądajmy telewizję! Mam przekąski.
Really, don't worry about me.
Proszę się nie martwić.
That feels so good.
Wspaniałe uczucie.
I'm so happy, Daddy. That's so good!
Tak mi dobrze, tatusiu!
Daddy... that's...
Tatusiu...
I want to have all of you.
Pragnę ciebie całego!
Please!
Proszę!
Makoto is involved with the yakuza?
Makoto pracuje dla yakuzy?
Are you sure?
Na pewno?
Himeka is a bit of an airhead, but she wouldn't make this up.
Himeka bywa głupia, ale tego by nie zmyśliła.
What should we do?
Co zrobimy?
Watch out!
Uwaga!
Watch where you're going, kid! You should apologize!
Patrz, jak leziesz, gówniaro! Przeproś!
Yes, that's correct.
Zgadza się.
Your deceased husband has another child who will be turning 20 this year.
Pani zmarły mąż ma drugiego syna, który kończy w tym roku 20 lat.
He's very upset right now.
Jest wściekły.
That's too loud!
Za głośno!
I'm sorry. Like I said, he's very upset, and he says he wants to go confront you.
Przepraszam. Jak mówiłem, jest wściekły i chce się sądzić.
-He has a lawyer and-- -Stop whining and just pay for it!
- Ma prawnika... - Nie jęcz, tylko płać!
-I'll set your house on fire! -Excuse me...
- Spalę ci dom! - Przepraszam...
What? The police?
Co? Policję?
Great! I dare you to call them!
Super, śmiało!
-I know people! -He is too loud.
- Znam ludzi! - Jest za głośny.
If something happens to me, they'll kill you!
Zabiją cię, jeśli coś mi się stanie!
What?
Co?
That's right, yeah!
Właśnie!
You should've said that from the beginning!
Trzeba było tak od razu!
Got it!
Mam!
What are our profits now?
Ile mamy?
-About 80 million yen. -80 million?
- Jakieś 80 milionów jenów. - Aż 80 baniek?
Quiet down.
Ciszej.
Profits of 80 million in only two weeks...
Zarobić 80 milionów w dwa tygodnie...
You're really something else, Kusano.
Nieźle, Kusano.
I knew you were a genius!
Zawsze miałem cię za geniusza.
It's 100% thanks to the new register.
To dzięki nowemu rejestrowi.
That's true. But at this rate, we can reach our goal, right?
Fakt. Ale dzięki temu osiągniemy cel.
No, not necessarily.
Niekoniecznie.
There's only 30 names left on the new register.
Zostało tylko 30 nazwisk.
We don't have many alternatives left.
Nie mamy innych.
If we go to them like, "We ran out of names,"
Jeśli powiemy, że się wyczerpały,
they'll probably kill us.
pewnie nas pozabijają.
If we don't do something, we're in trouble.
Jeśli czegoś nie wymyślimy, będą kłopoty.
You'll think of something.
Na coś wpadniesz.
What? How do you figure?
Skąd wiesz?
I feel like we can do anything as long as we have you.
Mam wrażenie, że przy tobie wszystko się uda.
I've only done boring work up until now, and nothing ever panned out for me.
Zawsze miałem nudne fuchy i nic mi nie wychodziło.
But I feel like anything I do with you will succeed.
Przy tobie wiem, że wszystko mi się uda.
I want to keep working with you even if it kills me.
Będę z tobą pracował nawet za cenę życia.
Kanbe-san said it too, right? To do whatever we have to do.
Pan Kanbe sam powiedział, że musimy zrobić wszystko.
That's not what he meant.
Nie to miał na myśli.
Hey, Kusano.
Kusano.
Why exactly are you working so hard at this job?
Dlaczego tak ciężko pracujesz?
Why?
Dlaczego?
-Well, because... -Your dad's treatment costs?
- Cóż... - Leczenie taty kosztuje?
You told me about that. But you've already paid that off, right?
Mówiłeś. Ale już je opłaciłeś.
Why are you continuing, then?
Dlaczego dalej to robisz?
You don't think about going back to normal?
Nie chcesz z tym skończyć?
-Normal? -Yeah, normal.
- Skończyć? - Tak.
I can't go back to normal.
Nie mogę z tym skończyć.
I mean, I won't.
Nie zrobię tego.
Some scary stuff happened,
Stało się coś strasznego,
but that woke me up to reality. There's no going back now.
co było jak kubeł zimnej wody. Nie mam już odwrotu.
I'm high on the adrenaline,
Nakręca mnie adrenalina.
and like you said, there's no other job like this.
Sam mówiłeś, że to niepowtarzalna robota.
I probably can't quit the money transfer scam anymore.
Nie mogę się już wycofać z robienia przekrętów.
That's right. No matter what happens...
Co by się nie działo...
I can't quit.
Nie mogę.
Mom?
Mamo?
Makoto. Explain this.
Makoto. Wyjaśnij mi to.
Okay.
Dobrze.